<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
  <!ENTITY GFDL SYSTEM "fdl-appendix.xml">
  <!ENTITY app "<application>GNOME War Pad</application>">
  <!ENTITY appversion "0.3.0">
  <!ENTITY manrevision "0.3.0">
  <!ENTITY date "May 23, 2004">
  <!-- Information about the entities
       The legal.xml file contains legal information, there is no need to edit the file.
       Use the appversion entity to specify the version of the application.
       Use the manrevision entity to specify the revision number of this manual.
       Use the date entity to specify the release date of this manual.
       Use the app entity to specify the name of the application. -->
]>

<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 0.3.0
  Last modified: May 23, 2001
  Maintainers:
               Lucas Di Pentima <lucas@lunix.com.ar>

  Translators:
               (translators put your name and email here)
-->



<!-- =============Document Header ============================= -->

  <article id="index" lang="en">
    <!-- please do not change the id; for translations, change lang -->
    
    <articleinfo>
      <title>&app; Manual v&manrevision;</title>
      <copyright>
	<year>2003, 2004</year>
	<holder>Lucas Di Pentima</holder>
      </copyright>
      
      <!-- translators: uncomment this:
      
      <copyright>
      <year>2001-2002</year>
      <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
    </copyright>
      
      -->
      
      &legal;
      
      <authorgroup>
	<author>
	  <firstname>Lucas</firstname>
	  <surname>Di Pentima</surname>
	  <affiliation>
	    <orgname>LUNIX Soluciones en GNU/Linux</orgname>
	    <address><email>lucas@lunix.com.ar</email></address>
	  </affiliation>
	</author>
      </authorgroup>

      <revhistory>
	<revision>
	  <revnumber>&app; Manual V &manrevision;</revnumber>
	  <date>2003-06-16</date>
	  <revdescription>
	    <para role="author">Lucas Di Pentima
	    <email>lucas@lunix.com.ar</email></para>
	  </revdescription>
	</revision>
	<revision>
	  <revnumber>&app; Manual V &manrevision;</revnumber>
	  <date>2004-05-23</date>
	  <revdescription>
	    <para role="author">Lucas Di Pentima
	    <email>lucas@lunix.com.ar</email></para>
	  </revdescription>
	</revision>
      </revhistory>

    </articleinfo>
    
    <!-- ============= Document Body ============================= -->
    
    <!-- ============= Introduction ============================== -->
    <sect1 id="sec:intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      
      <sect2 id="sec:aboutgwp">
	<title>About <abbrev>&app;</abbrev></title>
	
	<graphic fileref="figures/logo.png" align="center" scale="50%"/>
	
	<para>&app; is a <emphasis>VGA Planets</emphasis> client
	  for the GNOME platform. This project's objectives are to produce
	  a full-featured client, easy to use by new players but powerful
	  enough for experienced VGA Planets emperors.</para>
	
	<para>The final version of this program should include the basic
	  gaming capability, plus a good pack of statistical charts,
	  estimation tables and graphs and calculus dialogs. Also it'll
	  have scripting support using (maybe) the Python interpreter
	  embebbed, to allow easy and fast addition of features such as
	  estrategical resource administration, etc.</para>
	
	<para><abbrev>GWP</abbrev>'s user interface is being designed so
	  that most activities are centered around the
	  <emphasis>starchart</emphasis>, this way the player can keep a
	  global vision of the territory. For the UI design I took ideas
	  from various VGA Planets clients, such as Informer, VPA and
	  PCC, nevertheless GWP has its own unique style, as a result of
	  the blending of the best characteristics of such clients plus
	  some of my own ideas (and some of my friends ideas
	  too!).</para>
      </sect2>
      
      <sect2 id="sec:whatisvp">
	<title>What is <emphasis>VGA Planets</emphasis>?</title>
	
	<para>For this section, I'll extract a piece of the introduction
	  made by its creator, Tim Wisseman. You can read the whole
	  version at <ulink
	    url="http://www.vgaplanets.com/intro2.htm">http://www.vgaplanets.com/intro2.htm</ulink>.</para>
	
	<para><citation>VGA Planets is a graphical, multi-player, play by
	    electronic mail, space war game. This game simulates combat in
	    space between galactic scale empires. The game emphasizes
	    colonization of space and the development of the planets that
	    you will find, colonize and/or conquer. How well you develop
	    these resources will determine what kind of starships
	    (freighters and capital ships) you will be able to produce and
	    how well you will be able to defend your space and attack your
	    neighbors.</citation></para>
	
	<para><citation> This game is designed to be a strategic and
	    tactical game of warfare, but you will also need to be able to
	    build an economy and service your empire. With a well-developed
	    economic base you will have a greater potential for winning the
	    game.</citation></para>
	
	<para><citation>As the leader of your empire you are responsible
	    for all of the decisions that affect your growth and production
	    (except, of course, being attacked by your neighbor). You will
	    decide how to best develop your planets with the resources
	    available to you. You will decide what type of starship(s) to be
	    built at your starbase(s). You are the mastermind behind your
	    race and you are in a race to see which empire can first
	    conqueror the universe.</citation></para>
	
	<para><citation>At the start of the game you are left with a
	    homeworld, a low tech starbase, and two low tech
	    starships. These are the only things left of your former empire
	    since the nastiest Ion Storm ever recorded hit the Echo
	    Cluster. You will need to manage your planet's population,
	    money, minerals and other resources wisely, for these are your
	    only sources of production early in the game. If you manage them
	    well you will be able to quickly expand and broaden your
	    economic and mineral base, while still keeping a wary eye on
	    your potentially dangerous neighbors. Remember, while you are
	    growing and becoming stronger, so are your
	    neighbors.</citation></para>
	
	<para><citation>VGA Planets is designed to be able to handle from
	    two to eleven players in a play by mail (electronic mail) game
	    format. The game is designed to be played as a Net or Bulletin
	    Board System (BBS) game (as long as file transfers are permitted
	    and available), although it can be played solely on one
	    computer. Many of the Net players are playing using E-mail and
	    UUENCODE.</citation></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec:vpmechanics">
	<title>Game Mechanics</title>

	<para>The fact that VGA Planets is a
	<emphasis>play-by-email</emphasis> game means that is an
	offline kind of game, this is why the players have to follow
	certain steps when joining a game:</para>

	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The host generates RST (result) files, one for each
	    player.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The host send the RST files to the players (via
	    e-mail, or any other form).</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Each player receives their RST file and unpacks it
	      with some <abbrev>VP</abbrev> client.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Each player make their actions and generate the TRN
	      with some <abbrev>VP</abbrev> client.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The players send their TRN files to the host.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>The host receives the TRN files and proccess them,
	    check if some player is trying to cheat, and so on. Then,
	    go back to the first step.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>

      </sect2>
      
      <sect2 id="sec:games_internet">
	<title><abbrev>VP</abbrev> Games on the Internet</title>
	
	<para>Maybe you've never played this great game and would like
	  to give it a try, but you don't have any friends that know VGA
	  Planets, so...how to start?</para>
	
	<para>Fortunately, there are several websites dedicated to
	  host <abbrev>VP</abbrev> games, so that you can sign up to
	  any game and play with people all over the world. Some
	  interesting <abbrev>VP</abbrev> hosting sites are:</para>
	
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><ulink
		url="http://www.thelastdomain.com/vgaplanets.asp">The
		Last Domain VGA Planets</ulink></para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><ulink
		url="http://www.home.aone.net.au/neilgrigg/navgap.html">NAVGAP
		'VGA Planets' Hosting Service</ulink></para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><ulink
		url="http://vgaplanets.fontventa.com/home.htm">Sorcermon
		- VGA Planets Hosting</ulink></para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><ulink
		url="http://www.uk-gamerz.com/vgap/gamelist.htm">UK
		Gamers - VGA Planets Server</ulink></para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><ulink
		url="http://www.thedeepsouth.org/vgaindex.htm">The
		Deep South</ulink></para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><ulink
	    url="http://planetsserver.com/">Planetsserver.com</ulink></para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </sect2>
      
      <sect2 id="sec:learnmore">
	<title>Learn more about VGA Planets</title>

	<para>&app; is just a client, so this documentation is
	made to teach you how to use it, but it won't teach you how to
	play VGA Planets, that's a little more complicated.</para>

	<para>If you don't know how to play <abbrev>VP</abbrev>, then
	  you should visit <ulink
	    url="http://www.xs4all.nl/~donovan/">Donovan's Site</ulink>,
	  the best and more complete VGA Planets information site on
	  the Internet. There you'll have all the necessary to become
	  a great space conqueror.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec:game_mgr">
      <title>The Game Manager</title>
      
      <para>The game manager is an utility that &app; provides to
      store several game settings on a centralized fashion. As you can
	see on <xref linkend="fig:game_mgr"/>, it consists of an icon
      list, each icon representing a configured game.</para>

      <figure id="fig:game_mgr">
	<title>&app;'s Game Manager</title>
	<graphic fileref="figures/game-mgr.png"/>
      </figure>

      <para>You can add a new game, delete or edit an existing game's
      preferences, with no danger of modifying the real data
      files. The game manager only register game data on the GNOME
      registry subsystem.</para>

      <para>When you press the <guibutton>New</guibutton> button or
      edit an existing game, you'll see a dialog like the one shown at
	<xref linkend="fig:game_mgr_edit_game"/>, you have to select
      the game directory where your game data files reside, then the
      program will detect the available races and will show them on
      the list at the left.</para>

      <figure id="fig:game_mgr_edit_game">
	<title><quote>New/Edit Game</quote> dialog</title>
	<graphic fileref="figures/game-mgr-edit-game.png"/>
      </figure>

      <para>When the available races are listed, you have to click on
      the one you will use to play (this allows you to have many races
      within the same directory, and be able to play them all), and
      also type the game name, that will be used on the icon list
      previously shown.</para>

      <para>If the program detects that exists a RST file to be
	unpacked, the <guibutton>Unpack</guibutton> button will be
	activated so that you can execute that operation
	instantly.</para>

      <para>The other fields, as of version &appversion; are not being
	used for anything, you can leave them blank.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="sec:basic_usage">
      <title>&app; Basic Usage</title>

      <para>This client is very <emphasis>starchart
      centric</emphasis>, almost all the operations can be done from
      some kind of starchart view, so that the player can maintain a
      global view at the game.</para>

      <sect2 id="sec:starchart_keys">
	<title>Starchart keystrokes</title>

	<para>The Echo Cluster is a square of 2000 by 2000
	  light-years, the starchart provides the player an extra
	  view, a margin around the Echo Cluster of 500 LY wide. It
	  has grid, with 100 LY between lines.</para>

	<para>The keystrokes to scroll the starchart are:</para>

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><keycap>A</keycap>: Scroll left</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><keycap>D</keycap>: Scroll right</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><keycap>W</keycap>: Scroll up</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><keycap>S</keycap>: Scroll down</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>You can also scroll the starchart using the mouse, by
	  dragging it. Also, you can toggle the grid by pressing
	  <keycap>G</keycap> and zoom in and zoom out with
	  <keycap>+</keycap> and <keycap>-</keycap> from the
	  keypad.</para>

      <para>The planet names are automatically hidden when you zoom
      out below 100%, but if you want you can turn them off using the
      <guimenuitem>Planet names</guimenuitem> entry on the
      <guimenu>View</guimenu> menu. Similar actions you can make with
      minefields and ion storms.</para>

      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="sec:planet_ops">
	<title>Planet operations</title>

	<para>Each planet is represented by a tiny circle, if it's
	grey the planet is unknown, if it's green, the planet is
	ours. Planets with a green <emphasis>halo</emphasis>, are
	planets that have starbases orbiting, so that you can identify
	them quickly.</para>

	<figure id="fig:starchart">
	  <title>&app;'s StarChart</title>
	  <graphic fileref="figures/starchart.png"/>
	</figure>

	<para>As you can see on <xref linkend="fig:starchart"/>, when
	you click on a planet, a little red mark is placed around the
	selected planet and the most important data about that planet
	appears on the bar at the right. The idea of this is that you
	have only the important data with a fast, single-click on each
	planet. If you want more detailed information about the
	planet, just double-click on one, and two extra panels will
	appear, like the ones on <xref
	linkend="fig:starchart-planet"/></para>

	<para>At this mode, you can see all the data about the
	selected planet, and the starchart centers around the selected
	planet so you can see it sorroundings. You should note that
	the starchart scrolling functions are disabled in this view
	mode, you can return to full starchart view hitting the
	<keycap>Esc</keycap> key, or double-clicking on the planet
	again.</para>

	<para>On the lower left panel, there's a table with planet's
	future information, based on its actual state, this is very
	useful to establish long term strategies, this panel is
	intended to contain more and more of this type of charts,
	graphs, etc.</para>

	<figure id="fig:starchart-planet">
	  <title>Detailed information about a planet</title>
	  <graphic fileref="figures/starchart-planet.png"/>
	</figure>

      </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec:starbase_ops">
      <title>Starbase operations</title>

      <para>Inside the planet extended view, you have on the upper
      right corner the possibility to change to starbase view, there
      you'll have all the needed information about the actual
      starbase, asi you can see on the picture below.</para>

      <figure id="fig:starchart-starbase">
	<title>Information about a starbase</title>
	<graphic fileref="figures/starchart-starbase.png"/>
      </figure>

      <para>On future releases, the lower left panel will have several
      charts about the starbase providing you lots of valuable
      information.</para>

      <para>If the planet has no starbase, the corresponding
      information fields are obviously erased.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="sec:starship_ops">
      <title>Starship operations</title>

      <para>Ships on starchart are shown as little triangles, they're
      blue if the ships are our own, and red if not. This triangles
      are oriented specially to show the actual ship's heading, so you
      can be aware of that even without the need of selecting every
      ship.</para>

      <para>To select a ship you should right-click near it, the right
      panel switches to <emphasis>ship list mode</emphasis>, and show
      a complete list of every visible ship on the same spot,
      similarly to <xref linkend="fig:starchart-ship-simple"/>,
      drawing a green mark around the selected location.</para>

      <figure id="fig:starchart-ship-simple">
	<title>Ship list view</title>
	<graphic fileref="figures/starchart-ship-simple.png"/>
      </figure>

      <para>On the list you'll see the ship's ID and name, and
      selecting any of this list items will update the information
      below, showing a limited but vital set of ship data. If you
      double-right-click on the starchart, or double-click on the ship
      list, the extra panels will appear showing the rest of the
      ship's data and the corresponding ship image, just like <xref
      linkend="fig:starchart-ship-complete"/>.</para>

      <figure id="fig:starchart-ship-complete">
	<title>Complete ship info visualization</title>
	<graphic fileref="figures/starchart-ship-complete.png"/>
      </figure>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>
    
  <!-- APPENDIX: License -->
  &GFDL;
  
  </article>