    <sect1 id="whatisvp">
      <title>What is <emphasis>VGA Planets</emphasis>?</title>
      
      <para>For this section, I'll extract a piece of the introduction
	  made by its creator, Tim Wisseman. You can read the whole
	  version at <ulink
	    url="http://www.vgaplanets.com/intro2.htm">http://www.vgaplanets.com/intro2.htm</ulink>.</para>
      
      <para><citation>VGA Planets is a graphical, multi-player, play by
	    electronic mail, space war game. This game simulates combat in
	    space between galactic scale empires. The game emphasizes
	    colonization of space and the development of the planets that
	    you will find, colonize and/or conquer. How well you develop
	    these resources will determine what kind of starships
	    (freighters and capital ships) you will be able to produce and
	    how well you will be able to defend your space and attack your
	    neighbors.</citation></para>
      
      <para><citation> This game is designed to be a strategic and
	    tactical game of warfare, but you will also need to be able to
	    build an economy and service your empire. With a well-developed
	    economic base you will have a greater potential for winning the
	    game.</citation></para>
      
      <para><citation>As the leader of your empire you are responsible
	    for all of the decisions that affect your growth and production
	    (except, of course, being attacked by your neighbor). You will
	    decide how to best develop your planets with the resources
	    available to you. You will decide what type of starship(s) to be
	    built at your starbase(s). You are the mastermind behind your
	    race and you are in a race to see which empire can first
	    conqueror the universe.</citation></para>
      
      <para><citation>At the start of the game you are left with a
	    homeworld, a low tech starbase, and two low tech
	    starships. These are the only things left of your former empire
	    since the nastiest Ion Storm ever recorded hit the Echo
	    Cluster. You will need to manage your planet's population,
	    money, minerals and other resources wisely, for these are your
	    only sources of production early in the game. If you manage them
	    well you will be able to quickly expand and broaden your
	    economic and mineral base, while still keeping a wary eye on
	    your potentially dangerous neighbors. Remember, while you are
	    growing and becoming stronger, so are your
	    neighbors.</citation></para>
	
      <para><citation>VGA Planets is designed to be able to handle from
	    two to eleven players in a play by mail (electronic mail) game
	    format. The game is designed to be played as a Net or Bulletin
	    Board System (BBS) game (as long as file transfers are permitted
	    and available), although it can be played solely on one
	    computer. Many of the Net players are playing using E-mail and
	    UUENCODE.</citation></para>
    </sect1>
